Wrege, Charles D. Research Papers Regarding History of Management 5618
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Charles D. Wrege Research Papers Regarding History of Management
1928-1994
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Wrege, Charles D.
5618
4.44 cubic feet
4.4 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
Charles Wrege's research material, correspondence, some government publications, experiment data and miscellaneous research material used to write his papers.
3338516
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 11, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 21, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Charles "Chuck" Wrege finished his undergraduate degree in Upsala College, obtained his Masters degree at the New School fo Social Research and another Masters of Business Administration and his Ph.D. at NYU. He taught industrial management at Rutgers University for 30 years. He became a renowned historian, researcher and writer. He is regarded as a "National Treasure" by many in his field because of his expertise and the seminal research he has done in the area of management history.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5930 mf: Morris L. Cooke "Industrial Management" Monograph on Microfilm
Industrial management -- United States; Management -- Research -- United States; Management science.; Wrege, Charles D.
3338516
- "The Human Side of Enterprise" Forty-Five Years Before McGregor: The Work of Richard A. Feiss, Early Explorer In Human Relations, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  August 14- 17, 1977
- "The Search for Schmidt", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Charles D. Wrege: Working Paper, Academy of Management.
- Correspondence, Charles D. Wrege, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Concerns Feiss Research
- Feiss Material for Golden Book, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Charles D. Wrege
- Research Paper: Mary B. Gilson, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Research Paper: Mary B. Gilson, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous Articles on Scientific Management (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Article: "Taylor's Pig-Tale: A Historical Analysis of Frederick W. Taylor's Pig-Iron Experiments", 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Charles D. Wrege; Academy of Management Journal; March 1974
- "A Collection of Original F.W. Taylor Documents", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Charles D. Wrege; Compiled for the Academy of Management History Division
- N-File Newsletter, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Charles D. Wrege; Academy of Management; October 1978
- Background Material for Feiss Research (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Charles D. Wrege; Article by Henry Ruger, 1910
- Background Material for Feiss Research (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Background Material for Feiss Research (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Charles D. Wrege; Article by Henry Ruger, 1933
- Background Material for Feiss Research (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Background Material for Feiss Research (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Charles D. Wrege; Henry Link Article, 1923
- Background Material for Feiss Research (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Charles D. Wrege; Obituary: Henry Ruger, 1947
- Background Material on Feiss, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Charles D. Wrege; Sent by Mrs. Feiss to Lyndall Urwick; 4/30/1957
- "J.W. Starr, Cincinnati's Forgotten Genius", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Charles D. Wrege; Cincinnati Historical Society Bulletin; 1976
- Corrections to Feiss Paper, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Miscellaneous: Government Publications, 1922-1926 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Miscellaneous: Notes on Kurt Lewin (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Notes on R.A. Feiss (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Notes on Organization of Clothcraft (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Organization Chart of Employment and Service Department of Joseph and Feiss, Inc. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Transparencies. Charles D. Wrege
- Research Materials from "The Search for Schmidt", F.W. Taylor's Subject for Pig-Iron Experiments, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Charles D. Wrege; American Cemetery; September 1964
- Correspondence on "Search for Schmidt" (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Charles D. Wrege; Bethlehem Steel Co.
- Data on Taylor from Henry T. Boreman, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  On Pig-Iron 1963' Boreman is friend of Bob Brown of Bethlehem PA
- Correspondence on Edward Briggs (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Of Bethlehem; former foreman at Bethlehem Steel
- Correspondence with Mellville J. Boyer (Box 1, Folder 29)
  On "Search for Schmidt"
- Correspondence with Calvin Burk on Henry Noll (Box 1, Folder 30)
  (old volunteer foreman)
- Correspondence with City Clerk, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Bethlehem PA on Henry Noll's house at 313 Martins Lane
- Data on Bethlehem Steel's "Farm: (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Correspondence with Walter Kuhn on Noll, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Noll Family Chart, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  By Helen Lilly, 10/26/1963
- Correspondence on the "Search for Schmidt" (Box 1, Folder 35)
  with "Northampton County Historical and Genealogical Society"
- Questions Concerning Henry Noll, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Alias "Schmidt" 11/10/1964
- Correspondence on the "Search for Schmidt" (Box 1, Folder 37)
  With: Vernon Nelson Archives of the Moravian Church
- "Schmidt Data", 1963 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Data on Pig Iron Experiments (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Flow Chart for "Search for Schmidt", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  Working Paper
- Barth Chart on the Work of Hohn and Gansberger (Box 1, Folder 41)
  1894
- Forms for "Search for Schmidt", 1963 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  10/1/1963: Search for his house at 313 Martins Lane
- Forms for the "Search for Schmidt", 1963 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  Original form 9/10/1963
- Correspondence with Stuart Bolger, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Historic Bethlehem Inc.; Henry Noll ("Search for Schmidt")
- Data on Bethlehem Fabricators and Noll (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Names of Persons Mentioned in Gillespie and Wolle Study, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Correspondence with St. Michael's Cemetery, Bethlehem, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  On men in Taylor's Experiments
- Correspondence with Holy Saviour Cemetery, Bethlehem, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Correspondence on the "Search for Schmidt" (Henry Noll), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  With: John Stohmeyer Bethlehem Globe-Times; October 1 1963
- J. Boddewyn, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  "F.W. Taylor Revisited"; Journal of Academy of Management; August 1961
- Correspondence on the "Search for Schmidt", 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  With: Bethlehem Memorial Park (Mr. Speck, Mr. Harold Ziegenfuss)
- Photos of Noll (Box 1, Folder 52)
  Contains photographs
- Hawthorne Photos and Taylor "Flying Machine" (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Printer's Plates for Henry Noll Photographs, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  American Cemetery Magazine, 1964
- Data on Taylor, "Schmidt", etc. Album, 1958-1967 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Gilbraith (Box 1, Folder 56)
  Contains photocopies of photographs
- Correspondence with Robert Lovett at Harvard, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  On Mayo, etc.
- Western Electric Survey of Illumination and Efficiency (Box 1, Folder 58)
  11/18/140 Photocopy
- Western Electric Training Program, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Discussion by G.P. Mangan, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  Potomac Electric Power Co., Washington. DC; on lighting in Washington; August 2-4, 1926
- Notebook with Hawthorne Studies Data (Box 1, Folder 61)
  Letters, etc.
- Miscellaneous Hawthorne Data (Box 1, Folder 62)
- James E. Ives Study on Post Office Illumination Tests 1923, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  Reprint #973 from Public Health Reports, Vol. 39, #46; November 14, 1924 p.p. 2825 - 2851
- "Hawthorne", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  Arthur C. Moore
- Search for Harold Wright, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Western Electric News, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  George A. Pennock Data, Nov. 1927, p.p. 12-13
- Correspondence with Gerard Swope on Hawthorne, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  9/18/1957
- Michael Argyle's Comments on Relay Assembly Test Room in Retrospect, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Correspondence with Lyndall Urwick on Hawthorne, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Taylor-Thompson Letters, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Taylor Forms from Carl Barth (Box 2, Folder 2)
- F.B. Stearns Taylor-Barth Form (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Scientific Management Correspondence, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  J.C. Barth to Wrege 11/9/1960
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1948-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence with Phillip Wolle, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Frederick W. Taylor Souvenir Booklet, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- J.D. Cooke and Herman Hutkin, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Lecture Notes of Leon P. Alford, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  From Dr. Jon Glover of NYU
- Barth Charts of Benefits of Scientific Management, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Manuscript on Taylor for American Heritage, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Morris L Cooke Correspondence, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Reference Material on Taylor and Cooke and Industrial Management (Box 2, Folder 13)
- James Gillespie (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "Before Mayo, Forgotten Experiments and Experimenters at Hawthorne" (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Data on "Changes in Job Demand" and Creativity and Engineers (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Proposed textbook by Department of Management Science at Rutgers, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- C. Wrege Describing Accession, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  July 11th
- "Lizzie Likes Her Job", 1920 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Professor John R. Commons
- "Spring lake" (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Charles D. Wrege, Rutgers University
- Derer Study on Management Material in Chicago Libraries, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- A Survey of Foreign Industrial Human Relations Research, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Charles D. Wrege MBA These NYU
- Blueprints (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Will Bethlehem Follow Pittsburgh?, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Bethlehem Steel; Literary Digest; 8/6/1910
- J. Christian Barth Letters, 1959-1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Talk at Hanover PTA, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Charles D. Wrege; 3/13/1963; Clipping from The Weekly News of the Hanovers, 3/6/1963
- Charles D. Wrege data (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Analysis of Various 1926-1927 Illumination Tests (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence with Miles Tinker, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- 1919 Data on "Factorylite" (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Influence of Lighting, Eyesight, and Environment upon Work Production, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  US Government under Public Buildings Service; 1947
- NRFCA (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Proposal for free lamp renewal survey
- Lighting Campaigns Data, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  6/18/1968
- The Academy of Management, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Annual Membership Report August 1973
- Correspondence with John M. Burnham, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Photo of The Willimantic Linen Co. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Includes negative; Academy of Management
- History of Scientific Management, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  September 1939
- Photograph of H.C. Wolle at Bethlehem Iron Co, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  2/19/1897; Contains photograph
- Transparencies Set 1 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Analysis of writing and typing of Cooke and Taylor
- Transparencies Set 2 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Transparencies Set 3 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Transparencies Set 4 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Professor Hugo Meonsterberg (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Managementology, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  John G. Glover
- Charles Day Book Part 1, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Charles Day Book part 2, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Management History Film (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Contains VHS tape
- Hawthorne Interviews, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  September 9 1983; Contains VHS tape
- "Some Perspectives on the Hawthorne Studies", 1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Academy of Management Centennial, 1986; Charles D. Wrege as participant; contains VHS tape
- American Iron and Steel Works, 1877 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  AL Holley and Lenox Smith; March 30 1877; photocopy
- "A Graphical History of Work" (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Diagram with French title
- Midvale Steel and Ordnance Company Union Documents, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Letter from Phillip Wolle, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  On Hartley C. Wolle who conducted Pig-Iron study at Bethlehem Steel Co.; March 1966
- "Relative Cost Numbers", 1912 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Prepared by Horace King Hathaway for the Farrell Foundry and Machine Company, Ansonia, Connecticut; July 18 1912
- Midvale-Heppenstall Philadelphia, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  9/1/1957
- Midvale Steel Co. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Canal History and Technology Proceedings, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  March 12 1994
- A Collection of Original Frederick W. Taylor Documents, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Souvenir Booklet; 5 copies
- Scientific Management Methods as Applied to A Manufacturing Organization, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Richard A Feiss; 7/12/1928
- Coil Winding Department - tables [brittle and curled] (Box 5, Folder 1)
- C. Wrege describing gift of 7/11/1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)